Register of the Trotsky collection, 1917-1995
Hoover Institution Archives
- ADDENDUM, 1920-1995 (Box 46-47, art rack)
  - Subject File II, 1933-1995. (Box 47)
    - General, 1933-1989.
      - Feeley, Dianne, Paul LeBlanc and Thomas Twiss, “Leon Trotsky and the Organizational Principles of the Revolutionary Party,”, undated. (Box-folder 47: 3)
      - Hansen, Joseph, “Trotsky ‘Psychoanalyzed’” (review of Bernard Wolfe, The Great Prince Died), International Socialist Review, 1959, and “With Trotsky in Coyoacan” (introduction to Pathfinder Press edition of Leon Trotsky, My Life), 1970 (Box-folder 47: 4)
      - Rühle-Gerstel, Alice, “No Verses for Trotsky: A Diary in Mexico, 1937,” Encounter, 1982 April (Box-folder 47: 5)
      - Schlesinger, Rudolf, “Trotsky in the Crisis of the Civil War” (review of Jan M. Meier, ed., The Trotsky Papers, 1917-1922, Vol. I, 1917-1919), Science and Society, circa 1965 (Box-folder 47: 6)
      - Twersky, David, “The Second Life of Leon Trotsky,” Partisan Review, 1987 (Box-folder 47: 7)
      - Wilson, Edmund, “Trotsky,” New Republic, 1933 January 4, and “Trotsky,” Adelphi, 1933 July (Box-folder 47: 8)
      - Miscellaneous articles, 1978-1989 (Box-folder 47: 9)
        Mainly reviews of books about Trotsky
    - Assassination of Trotsky (motion picture film). Correspondence, 1971. (Box-folder 47: 10)
      Letters by Harold Robins, Esteban Volkov (grandson of Trotsky) and George Weissman
    - Deutscher, Isaac. Correspondence, notes and printed matter regarding Deutscher’s biographical trilogy about Trotsky, 1954-1964. (Box-folder 47: 11)
      Includes printed reviews by George Breitman, Tony Cliff and Joseph Hansen; typed translation of review by Pierre Frank; letters by Breitman and Jack Barnes; and notes by Barnes
    - Russian assessments. Material about late Soviet and post-Soviet Russian assessments of Trotsky, 1988-1995. (Box-folder 47: 12)
      Includes Thomas Sherlock, “Reassessing the Historical Image of Trotsky” (typescript) and printed articles by Robin Blackburn, Alexander Pantsov, Marilyn Vogt-Downey and Mikhail Voyeikov
    - “Trotskyist” as label. Memorandum by George Breitman and excerpts from Socialist Workers Party minutes, 1951-1966, regarding discussion of use of term “Trotskyist” as descriptive label by party (Box-folder 47: 13)
  - Artwork, undated. (Art rack)
    Portrait of Natalia Sedova Trotsky, wife of Leon Trotsky, painted by Evelyn Reed.